Guide to the David Andrew Hunter Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
David Andrew Hunter papers
1942-1958
MS 1486
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1
(4 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence, topical files and photographs. Correspondence and topical files document David Hunter's attempts to prove that his post-war illnesses were service-related and to gain compensation. The photographs are of the Far East during World War II.
Hunter, David Andrew, 1904-1958
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of David A. Hunter, Jr., 1988.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged in three series: Series I. Correspondence, 1942-1958. Series II. Topical Files, 1942-1958. Series III. Photographs, 1958, undated
Biographical / Historical
David Andrew Hunter was born on March 24, 1904 in New Orleans, Louisiana. He graduated from Warren Easton High School in 1921. He studied for one year at Tulane University and eventually worked at Kessler Insurance Company in New Orleans. He married Belle Watson in 1930. Their son, David Andrew Hunter, Jr. was born in 1931. David Hunter, Sr. enlisted in the Army on June 23, 1942 in New Orleans. As an Intelligence Officer in the Office of Strategic Services, Hunter served in Burma, India, China and Thailand. Hunter received an honorable discharge on April 6, 1946, and returned to New Orleans. Thereafter, he became ill with dysentery and malaria. He attempted to prove his illness was service-related in order to receive compensation, but was unsuccessful. David Andrew Hunter died on May 19, 1958.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence, topical files and photographs. Correspondence and topical files document David Hunter's attempts to prove that his post-war illnesses were service-related and to gain compensation. The photographs are of the Far East during World War II.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Military pensions; Veterans -- Medical care; Veterans -- United States; World War, 1939-1945 -- Campaigns -- Burma; World War, 1939-1945; Burma -- History -- Japanese occupation, 1942-1945; Hunter, David Andrew, 1904-1958; United States. Office of Strategic Services
- Correspondence, 1942-1958; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence is arranged in two sections: "Family" and "Other." Within each section, letters are arranged chronologically. The "Family" section contains letters written by Hunter to his wife and son during his service in World War II. The letters reveal very little about the course of the war or Hunter's role in it. Hunter comments mainly on family matters and foreign culture and landscapes. The "Other" section primarily includes letters written by non-family members on behalf of Hunter in his attempt to gain compensation for his illnesses. Typically, the writers address the capacity in which they were familiar with Hunter and praise his character. Copies of Hunter's solicitations for such assistance are frequently attached.
  - Family
    - 1942
      - June 27-July 30 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - August 1-September 30 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - October 1-December 30 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1943
      - January 7-March 23 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - April 1-June 30 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - July 3-August 26 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - September 6-December 5 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1944
      - March 6-May 31 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - June 1-August 29 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - September 4-November 1 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - 1949-1956, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Other, 1942 December 2-1958 April 8 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Topical Files, 1942-1958, undated; Series II
  This series is arranged alphabetically. Most materials relate to Hunter's medical problems and attempts to obtain compensation from the Red Cross, Social Security Administration and Veteran's Administration. The "Medical record" file is the most informative pertaining to his illnesses. "Military record" provides extensive biographical information. "Memos and directives" includes information on Hunter's military transfers and duties. "Prisoners of War, Siam" contains a draft by Hunter of a work that describes the American prisoners of war he evacuated from Siam in August, 1945.
  - American National Red Cross, 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Finances, 1942 October - 1958 June 16 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Medical [background reference file], 1948, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Medical record, 1944-1956 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Memos and directives [military], 1942-1953 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Military record, 1946-1953 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous, 1942, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1942-1945 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Postcards [Seminoles in Florida], Undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Prisoners of War, Siam, Undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Rangoon [victory celebrations], 1945 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Social Security Administration, 1958, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Veteran's Administration
    - Affidavits, 1948-1956 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Claims and compensation ratings, 1947-1958 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Photographs, 1958, undated; Series III
  Photographs are arranged in two sections: "Identified" and "Unidentified." Within these sections they are arranged alphabetically by topic. The majority are undated. They are comprised of black and white photographs, 2" x 3.5", 3" x 5", and 8" x 10". On the whole, the photographs are in good condition, but some have faded. A few of the 8" by 10" photographs are of superior quality. This is the most interesting series in the collection. It contains hundreds of photographs of the landscape, culture, indigenous peoples and American soldiers in the Far East during World War II.
  - Identified
    - Ba Maun Chain, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Battle Creek Hotel, Undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Bunker, Japanese, Undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Donovan, General William and Colonel Ray Peers, Undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Hunter, David A., Undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Hunter, David A., General William Donovan and Colonel Ray Peers, Undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Peers, Colonel Ray, Undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Photograph in 'Behind the Burma Road' [aerial], Undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Unidentified, Undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Aerial (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Airplanes (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Celebrations (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Cities (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Civilian (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Commissary (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Construction (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Corpses (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Hunting (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Indigenous peoples
      - General (Box 3, Folder 11-12)
      - Children (Box 3, Folder 13)
      - Girl (Box 3, Folder 14)
      - Troops (Box 3, Folder 15)
      - Women (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Japanese flags (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Landscapes (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Medical [war hospitals] (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Skulls, enemy [American display] (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Soldiers, United States (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Soldiers, United States with indigenous peoples (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Torture victims (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Villages (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - War damage (Box 4, Folder 25)